in this video we are going to data my
novel chart patterns with python I'll
outline an approach to find High
performing patterns in the price
structure on any Market the
visualization you are seeing now is the
current price structure pattern drawn in
white we will save and normalize each of
these shapes then group them into
clusters to find recurring patterns in
price structure we will assess the
future behavior of the market after
these price structure patterns manifest
to find profitable patterns if you like
more advanced algorithmic trading
content like this consider subscribing
there are three main steps in this
approach first we build a data set of
price shapes then we cluster the data
set into groups of similar patterns then
we assess and select the best patterns
that tend to proceed a move in the price
first we need to build our data set in
this example we are finding five
perceptually important points on the
recent 24 candles of data if you are
unfamiliar with the perceptually
important Point algorithm I covered in
detail in my chart pattern algorithms
video linked in the corner but quickly
the perceptually import important Point
algorithm always selects the first and
last points on a section of data then
selects additional internal points by
finding the points with the maximum
distance from two adjacent selected
points I drew lines between the Five
Points to make it a little easier to see
but these Five Points serve as a summary
of The Price action over the last 24
candles of data this reduces
dimensionality which makes it much
easier and faster for clustering
algorithms or other algorithms to
process we compute the perceptually
important points for each subsequence of
24 candles across the entire data set
and record them we will cluster these
subsequences to find similar groups this
idea originated in 2001 with the
publication of this paper you may have
noticed earlier but as this
visualization runs the pattern shape
does not update with each new candle
there's an important reason for this in
2003 this paper was published that
critiqued the 2001 paper it claimed
subsequence clusters are meaningless
this paper goes into great detail and it
is worth reading if you're interested in
pattern Discovery for trading but in
short adjacent subsequences are not
unique they have considerable overlap
this overlap causes trivial matches and
causes the patterns found to be
essentially random the authors of the
2001 paper made an update to their
method to prevent meaningless pattern
Discovery in this 2005 paper this
updated method is the one we will use we
compute the perceptually important
points with a sliding window on the
recent 24 candles but only included in
the data set at the internal
perceptually important points are
different from the last subsequence this
change causes each subsequence to be
more unique and avoid trivial
meaningless clusterings it also reduces
the total amount of subsequences to
Cluster which reduces the processing
time an added bonus let's look at the
code for this
the code for the entire data mining
process is managed by a class pip
pattern Miner we first load in some data
from a CSV we convert the prices to
logarithmic prices the class assumes
that the prices are logarithmic so this
must be done we get the closing price as
an array then we create an instance of
the class it has three parameters the
number of perceptually important points
the look back which is the number of
candles the Pips will be found on and
the hold period the hold period will be
discussed more later but it is how many
candles a position will be held after a
selected pattern is found we pass our
closing price array to the classes train
function the n-wraps parameter will be
discussed later here is the init
function of the class it doesn't do
anything but declare variables the main
thing of note for now is the input
parameters are saved in these values
here is the train function we save the
closing price array as data in the class
then we call this function find unique
patterns this function handles the
creation of the unique pit patterns
which we will cluster later we will keep
track of the coordinates of the last
subsequence in this list we Loop through
each candle in the data set we find the
most recent section of the data and
store it in this variable window when we
initiated the class we set look back to
24 so window contains the 24 most recent
closing prices we find the perceptually
important points on the recent data we
update the x coordinates of the
perceptually important points to match
the indices of the entire array we Loop
through the internal perceptually
important points ignoring the first and
last and compare them to the last set
found if there is a difference found we
set the Boolean same to false and break
if the internal points are not the same
we record the perceptually important
points as a unique pattern we Z score
normalize the price values by
subtracting their mean and dividing by
the standard deviation this will cause
each pattern to have a similar price
scale which allows us to Cluster price
patterns at different times throughout
the data we record our normalized
pattern and the current index finally we
update the indices of the last bound
perceptually important points then
continue looping through the rest of the
data set after we have done this we have
a collection of unique patterns the
prices made throughout the data given I
should note that we do not pay attention
to the time between the points making up
the pattern just the levels of price
throughout the pattern now with our
collection of normalized price patterns
we will cluster them into similar groups
there is a large variety of clustering
algorithms each with its own merits and
weaknesses but one important feature we
need is the ability to classify new
observations into a cluster this way we
can use the found patterns on out of
sample data I'm going to elect to use
the simple well-known k-means clustering
this algorithm clusters data into a set
number of clusters the cluster centers
are the mean values of all the samples
within a cluster new samples can be
assigned to a cluster by finding the
cluster sensor that is the closest to it
I won't cover the algorithm here but
there are many resources available
online explaining it if you are
unfamiliar when clustering these pattern
shapes with the K means algorithm we
have an important decision to make how
many clusters do we use if we use less
clusters then the amount of price shapes
in each cluster will be higher which
allows us to have a higher sample size
and thus higher confidence when we
assess the performance of the cluster of
price shapes however using less clusters
will group price shapes that are less
similar so we may miss out on a truly
good pattern that exists but is lumped
in with less Salient price shapes there
is no perfect solution to this problem
and it is certainly something requiring
further research but a decent approach I
found is using the silhouette method the
silhouette method scores each sample for
how well it fits into its cluster
samples that fit nicely toward the
center of their cluster score high while
samples that are on the Outer Edge lying
in between two clusters will get a lower
score the silhouette score can be
averaged across all samples and this
gives us an idea of how well the
clustering performs by using this method
we can compare the silhouette score when
using k-means with 5 clusters versus 10
clusters and select the better forming
amount of clusters I'll leave the
citation for the silhouette method in
the description if you want more detail
but thankfully there is a python library
to do the work for us so let's look at
the code for clustering to do the
clustering we will use the pi clustering
Library
these are the Imports that we need
this is the same train function we saw
earlier after finding the unique
perceptually important Point patterns we
use the silhouette case search to try
different amounts of clusters I have it
set to try five clusters up to 40
clusters we get the best amount of
clusters from the silhouette search then
we call the function k-means cluster
with the amount the silhouette method
deemed best the K means clustering
algorithm needs initial cluster centers
to start the optimization we get the
initial centers with the k-means plus
plus initializer then we pass the
initial clusters and the unique pit
patterns to the k-means instance and
process we get the cluster centers and
cluster membership of each sample and
the data set at this point the price
shapes are placed into clusters now we
assess the Clusters and select the ones
that precede movements in price to
assess the performance of each cluster I
employ a simple holding period each time
a pattern of a given cluster is found we
look at the Market's price change over
the next H candles in the example we've
used so far we have found five
perceptually important points on 24
candles of data since we are looking at
patterns that span 24 candles I think a
natural holding period would be less
than 24. I chose 6 as 1 4 of the pattern
length seems like a reasonable
prediction Horizon this choice is fairly
arbitrary but we have to pick something
over the course of the training set we
will find the Martin ratio for each
cluster the Martin ratio is calculated
by dividing the total return by the
ulcer index the ulcer index is
calculated by summing the squared
drawdown at each candle in the data set
this causes the Martin ratio to be
punished by both the length and depth of
drawdowns if a cluster of patterns have
smaller drawdowns or recover quickly
from drawdowns then they will have a
higher margin ratio the developer of the
Martin ratio has an excellent article
describing it in detail which I linked
below after we find the Martin ratio for
each cluster we will select the best
pattern for trading long and the best
pattern for trading short we will
combine the signals of the best long and
short patterns then compute the Martin
ratio on the combined version this will
be our final performance figure let's
look at the code for this back looking
at the train function I didn't mention
this earlier but at the start we compute
the logarithmic returns of the closing
price and shift them forward by one
candle we will use these returns in a
moment after clustering the patterns we
call the function git cluster signals
and here's the function we Loop through
each cluster found for each cluster we
create a signal concurrent with the
closing press array we passed in earlier
we initialize it as all zeros we Loop
through each member of the cluster we
get the index in the closing price array
that this cluster member or pattern
happens the index is the last candle in
the pattern we set the signal array to 1
for the set hold period we used six so
this will add six ones after this
pattern occurred to the signal array
then we add our signals to the this list
it is a class variable back to the train
function after Computing our cluster
signals we call the assign clusters
function we Loop through each cluster we
multiply the cluster signal by the
logarithmic Returns the cluster signal
is composed of zeros and ones so this
gives us all the returns that a cluster
was exposed to the market we compute the
Martin ratio from these returns we'll
look at this function in a second but
now it returns a number we record the
Martin ratio for each cluster after the
loop we find the cluster index of the
highest margin ratio this is the best
long pattern then we find the cluster
index of the lowest Martin ratio this
will be our short pattern we record the
long and short pattern in these lists I
experimented with selecting multiple
patterns and I used a list to record
these selected patterns here is the mark
ratio function it is passed an array of
log returns we first sum the returns if
the sum is negative we set this Boolean
as true lagging for short trading and we
we also flip the signs we get the
cumulative sum of returns we
exponentiate them for computing
percentage drawdown we also convert it
to a panda series to use the cumulative
Max function in this line we are
dividing the current sum of returns by
the max sum we've seen so far we
subtract one from this quotient this
gives us the percentage drawdown at each
candle we Square this percentage and sum
the squared percentage at each bar this
is the ulcer index we complete the ulcer
index by dividing by the size of the
array and taking the square root the
Martin ratio is the total return divided
by the ulcer index if we flag these
returns as a short pattern earlier we
set the Martin ratio to negative this
way the best long pattern will be the
maximum value found and the best short
pattern will be the minimum value found
back to the train function once more we
find our final margin ratio with this
function get total performance this
function is built to handle selecting
multiple long and short patterns if you
want to experiment but it works just
fine with just the one selected here we
create a long and short signal of zeros
for the length of the data we Loop
through each cluster if the cluster is a
member of the selected long patterns we
add the cluster signal to the long
signal if the cluster is a member of the
selected short patterns we add the
cluster signal to the short signal we
divide the signals by the number of
selected patterns in this case it's just
one so no effect we multiply the short
signal by negative one to flip the signs
we combine the signals by adding them we
multiply the combined signal by the
returns then we pass these combined
returns to the get Martin function we
covered earlier at this point we found a
pattern for trading long and a pattern
for trading short from the data let's
run this program on two years of hourly
Bitcoin data from the beginning of 2018
to the end of 2019 the silhouette method
decided that 16 clusters was the best
amount here are the cluster centers of
the long and short patterns discovered
the long pattern is shown in green
screen while the short pattern is shown
in red here is every member of the
Clusters found in the test period the
patterns are fairly loose there is quite
a bit of variation around the cluster
centers here are the cumulative log
returns of the long short and combined
patterns on the in-sample data they look
pretty good but these are in Sample
results we selected these patterns
because they were the best so there is a
strong selection bias in these results
to compare the strength of the selection
bias versus the strength of the actual
patterns in the data we will perform a
Monte Carlo permutation test to do this
we will permute the price returns to
create a new permuted price path this
permeated price path has an identical
return distribution but all the
legitimate patterns that may or may not
be present on the actual path are
destroyed all that remains in the
permitted price path isn't always we
will run our entire procedure again on
this primitive price path build our
unique perceptually important Point
patterns cluster them and select the
best performing clusters we will compare
the Martin ratio we find on the permuted
path to the one we found on the actual
price path if the result we find on the
permitted price path is weaker than what
we find on the actual price path then
that serves as evidence that there are
legitimate patterns in the actual data
the more times we permeate the price and
do this test the more evidence we gain I
generated 100 permutations of the price
from the start of 2018 to the end of
2019 and found the Martin ratio for each
of them here are the Monte Carlo test
results the Martin ratio is found on
each of the permutations is displayed as
a histogram while the Martin ratio on
the actual price is displayed as a red
line the actual data is ahead of all the
permutations this is good evidence that
there is something present in the actual
data that is not present in the price
permutations let's look at the code for
the Monte Carlo test the Monte Carlo
permutation function is controlled by
this parameter and Reps the number of
Monte Carlo repetitions we will use it
defaults to negative 1 which means we
don't do the amount Monte Carlo test
after we have finished the entire
procedure on real data we are left with
the final Martin ratio of the combined
best long and short pattern we save this
in the variable fit Martin we return
here if the Monte Carlo test is disabled
we Loop for each of the repetitions
requested these two lines Shuffle the
log returns of the original data we
concatenate the first value of the
original array and the shuffled returns
we set the class variable data as the
cumulative sum of the shuffled returns
now we do everything exactly the same as
we did before but this time we are using
permuted data we find the unique pit
patterns cluster them find the cluster
signals select the best then we get our
final performance figure on the
permeated data this is what we compare
to the performance figure found on real
data we save this performance figure
from the permuted data into this list
we've seen that our data mining process
is finding something stronger on real
data than it finds on noise or muted
data so at this point we'll try using
our found patterns on out of sample data
we will use a walk forward test to see
if our patterns work on out of sample
data I'll again use hourly Bitcoin data
but from the beginning of 2018 to the
end of 2022 we will train on two years
of data and test on one year of data so
in this case finding patterns with 2018
and 2019 data then testing them on 2020
then training on 2019 and 2020 and
testing on 2021 and so on let's look at
the code for this and then I'll show the
results before we go over the walk
forward code there is one more function
we need to go over in the pit pattern
minor class the class we've been looking
at so far this function predict is for
out of sample use it takes a list of
perceptually important points as input
we z-score normalize the input then we
Loop through all the cluster centers and
find the cluster center that is the
closest to the input this line here
finds the euclidean distance between the
in input and the center if the closest
Center is one of the selected long
patterns we return one at the closest
Center is one of the short patterns we
return negative one otherwise we return
zero here is the script for the walk
forward test we load data in from a CSV
then convert the data into logarithmic
prices we get the closing price array we
create an instance of this class WF pip
minor which is short for walk forward
perceptually important Point minor we
will look at this class in a second but
we pass in the parameters for the
pattern mining npips look back and hold
period we have already discussed the
train size is set to two years and
hourly data and the step size is set to
one year in hourly data we create a
signal list of zeros the same size as
the array we Loop through each index in
the array and call the classes update
signal method to fill out our signal
list this function Returns the current
signal for that index in the array after
the loop we add the signal to the data
frame compute the next turns and
multiply the signal by the returns to
get the out of sample returns let's look
at the class and the initialize function
we save our inputs and do class
variables next train is the index of the
closing price array when we will find
the patterns these variables hold the
current signal and hold period of the
system we create an instance of the pit
pattern minor class which we already
went over with the inputs specified the
class has only one function update
signal we already saw the loop that uses
it we check if the current index is
equal to the next train variable if it
is we call the train function of the
pattern mining class we update the next
train variable by adding the step size
we keep track of the hold period and
signal with these two if statements if
the current hold period is above one we
decrement if the whole period is zero we
set the current signal to zero at each
index we find the current perceptually
important points we pass the Y values of
the points into the predict function the
predict function returns 0 1 or negative
one if the return value is not 0 we set
the current signal and set the hold
period to the value specified then
return the current signal here are the
out of sample results this is the
cumulative log returns from the walk
forward code we just saw it is the
combined performance of both long and
short patterns found we can see that the
patterns found on 2018 and 2019 did very
well throughout 2020 but the performance
decayed afterward essentially flat
assumes the patterns found in Prior data
did not continue to work into 2021 and
2022 but the performance of 2020 shows
this type of strategy has some potential
what we did in this video is find
similar structures in price and attempt
to build trading patterns from them what
I showed only scratches the surface of
what is possible the code shown should
be viewed more as a toy than a fully
fledged trading system it has a long way
to go the results are not Stellar but I
wanted to show a complete example of
pattern mining a major issue with this
implementation is the clustering is
highly dependent on the the random seed
it will return different clusters each
run this Randomness is from the
initialization of the Clusters solving
for the optimal K means is an MP hard
problem and what we actually get is only
a local Optimum also each portion of the
algorithm has plenty of room for
improvement we could better represent
the patterns we could find a better way
to Cluster or even skip the Clusters and
do a nearest neighbor approach we could
also evaluate the patterns differently
Beyond a simple hold period but
hopefully this video gives you some
ideas for your own trading and research
I would like to make more videos on this
topic in the future there is quite a bit
to be done that's it for this one thank
you for watching